[Waco] Calvary Baptist Church records, Inclusive: 1929-1955, undated, Bulk: 1932-1955, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
[Waco] Calvary Baptist Church records
Inclusive: 1929-1955, undated, Bulk: 1932-1955, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3822
Calvary Baptist Church
1 document box
The [Waco] Calvary Baptist Church records consists of literary documents created by church members including church publications and a directory.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Calvary Baptist Church of Waco, Texas, was organized in 1928 February. The church resulted in the merging of two local congregations, the Brook Avenue Baptist and Provident Heights Baptist churches. Calvary Baptist continues to serve the greater Waco community.
Brook Avenue Baptist, located on the rear lot of Seventh Street and Brook Avenue, and Provident Heights Baptist, 1100 North 18th Street, were organized in 1909. In the seventeen years of each institution’s existence, a combined eleven pastors served the congregations. When the two churches consolidated, Provident Heights had a debt of $25,000 from a construction project of a permanent brick building. The combining of the two churches released their mutual pastors from service.
On 1928 February 5 the churches met and voted on the churches’ consolidation, the new organization’s name and chairman, church covenant, and articles of faith. A nominating and pulpit committee was organized and began the search for a pastor for the newly established Calvary Baptist Church, North 18th and Bosque Boulevard. On 1928 April 1 Reverend A. J. Holt began his services as the first pastor. He was a graduate of Baylor University and Southwestern Baptist Theological Seminary and a trustee of Hillcrest Baptist Hospital. The records in this collection were created during his tenure as pastor. In 1953, he was awarded an honorary Doctor of Divinity Degree from Baylor. Dr. Holt concluded his services as pastor on 1958 May 31.
During Dr. Holt’s tenure, the church began its first major building projects. The first was the construction of a second education building, erected in 1937, a nursery constructed in 1947, and a new auditorium in 1954. The new auditorium also housed new offices, a pastor’s study, choir room, and Fellowship Hall with a stage and kitchen. In 1955, all church buildings were air-conditioned. Calvary Baptist Church continues to worship, minister, and serve the people of Waco and surrounding communities.
Scope and Content
The [Waco] Calvary Baptist Church records begin in 1929 and ends in 1955 and have one series, Literary Productions.
The majority of the literary materials were final versions of church publications printed at an unknown local printing shop.The publications include church bulletins, Sunday school attendance cards, and letterheads. An envelope was stapled to each copy along with drafts of the final version of the publication. A unique feature of the collection is an unusual code in the undated church directory. Written on the inside of the church directory binder was an alphabetical code indicating the attendance history of Calvary Baptist Church. The following is the code for the directory: an H indicates persons who are members of a local church but who attend less than monthly, an E, persons who are members of a church in another city, an S, children born after 1958 who attend neither church nor Sunday school, and the letter N denotes persons who are not members of any church
Arrangement
The Calvary Baptist Church publications were inventoried and organized for the first time before the creation of this finding aid. Currently, the [Waco] Calvary Baptist Church records are arranged in one series: I. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3822. Acquired 0-00-00
Related Resources
Related references
“Calvary Baptist Celebrates Merging of Churches Today.” Waco Tribune Herald. 1963 February 3.
Waco, Texas: Churches: Calvary Baptist [vertical file], Brochures, The Texas Collection, Baylor University.
Index Terms
Subjects
Baptists -- Texas -- Waco.; Baptists -- Texas.; City churches -- Texas -- Waco.; McLennan County (Tex.) -- Church history.; Waco (Tex.) -- Church history.
Genres
Directories.; Publications (documents).
- Literary Productions, 1932-1955, undated
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Literary Productions series contains the final copy of church publications that were printed at an unknown local printing shop. In addition, there are two memorandum books and an undated church
  directory. This series is in average to good condition.
  - Church Publications, 1932-34 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Church Publications, 1935-37 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Church Publications, 1938-42 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Church Publications, 1943-46 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Church Publications, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Church Publications, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Church Publications (1 of 2), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Church Publications (2 of 2), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Church Publications, 1950, 1952-54 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Church Publications, 1955-undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Memorandum Book, 1928-29, 1932-37, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Memorandum Book (1 of 3), 1929-31, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorandum Book (2 of 3), 1929-31, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Memorandum Book (3 of 3), 1929-31, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Church Directory (1 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Church Directory (2 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Church Directory (3 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Church Directory (4 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Church Directory (5 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Church Directory (6 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Church Directory (7 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Church Directory (8 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Church Directory (9 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Church Directory (10 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Church Directory (11 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Church Directory (12 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Church Directory (13 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Church Directory (14 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Church Directory (15 of 15), undated (Box 1, Folder 29)